Well, now that US neutrality during
World War II was sumearily flushed down
the toilet thanks to Japan's bombing of
Pearl Harbor, I reckon that means it's
time to start mobilizing. And I further
reckon that we ought to talk about all
the effects there onto appertaining. So,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, so the
first major effect of US mobilization
during World War II is that it played a
big role in ending the Great Depression.
Now, like I mentioned in the previous
video, President Roosevelt tried
slapping the depression with all kinds
of different New Deal programs. But for
the most part, that depression just kept
depressing. But as it turned out, firing
up the engine of American industry to
mobilize for the war was the particular
smack needed to cure the profound ills
of the depression. And why says you?
Well, says I. In order to manufacture
all the supplies needed for the war, the
federal government employed nearly 4
million Americans and spent
unprecedented amounts of money under
Roosevelt's vision to make the United
States an arsenal for democracy. And as
a result, the US GDP increased by 50%
and industrial productivity nearly
doubled. And American unemployment fell
by about 85% in a matter of a few
months. And if you've been paying
attention for the last few videos, I
don't think I need to explain why that
was such a big deal, but you know, I
will. So, the prosperity of the 1920s
was largely owing to the focusing of the
economy on the mass production of
consumer goods, and that means precisely
two things. One, the industrial
infrastructure needed to produce all
those toasters and vacuum cleaners and
automobiles expanded wildly to keep up
with demand. Two, American consumers had
plenty of money to spend on those new
toys. And even if they didn't have the
money, the expansion of buying goods on
credit ensured that they could get
whatever they wanted. But when the
depression hit, no one had any money to
spend on those goods. And so production
dried up tighter than an old trucker's
elbow. But even if no one is buying
consumer goods, guess what still exists?
Yeah, it's all those new industrial
factories that were built to produce
those goods. And before I tell you
exactly why that was such a big deal,
let me just mention that if you need
help getting an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May, you might want
to check out my A Push Heimler review
guide. It is the fastest and sassiest
way to study for your exam. So if that's
something that you're into, get your
clicky finger out and check that link in
the description. Anyway, what I'm trying
to say is during the Great Depression,
all the industrial infrastructure for
prosperity already existed, but there
were no buyers. But once mobilization
began, US industry got one particular
buyer with real deep pockets and a real
itch to spend money, namely big daddy
government. And remember, that was kind
of Roosevelt's whole thing. Like the
Keynesian economics that guided the New
Deal programs was big on government
spending in order to correct for
economic failure, which is what they
called priming the pump. And so when it
was time to mobilize, the federal
government got busy priming the crap out
of that American economic pump. And much
of that growth was possible because
Roosevelt created the War Production
Board in order to coordinate government
manufacturing needs with private
corporations. For example, prior to the
war, the Boeing Corporation built a
modest amount of military and civilian
aircraft. But during mobilization,
Boeing received massive government
contracts and money. And in response,
the company rapidly increased its
production capabilities by creating
bombers on a scale previously unheard
of. And then similar results occurred
across other American industries,
including Marinhip, which built warships
and agricultural corporations and
textile companies, etc. The point is the
combination of huge demand and central
planning from the government greatly
expanded the US industrial capacity and
its output in a very short time. And it
was that unique large-scale industrial
capacity that contributed significantly
to the Allied victory in World War II.
Okay. Now, the second effect of
mobilization for the war was that the
process opened opportunities for some
Americans to improve their
socio-economic position. And there are
three groups that you should know.
First, new opportunities opened for
women. So, all that fabulous industrial
output I was just flapping my mouth hole
about faced one big hairy obstacle.
namely that men held the vast majority
of industrial jobs. And the government
wasn't going to get much out of this
fantastic industrial capacity if it was
shipping all of its working men across
the world to make the bang bang and the
pew pew. Therefore, in order to keep
American industry running at the pace
needed to win the war, women filled many
of these jobs. And I know that might
worry you since I mentioned in the last
unit that the general opinion of the
medical establishment at the end of the
19th century and the beginning of the
20th century was that women were by
nature ills suited for work. I mean, if
doctors were worried that women riding
bikes would ruin their faces and more to
the point, their ovaries, then what on
earth would happen to those poor
creatures if they took up work in
factories? Well, it turned out that
women prove themselves just as capable
as men in turnurning out industrial
goods for the war and their faces and
ovaries, miracle of miracles, survived.
Now, Rosie the River became an enduring
icon of women's industrial work at home
and demonstrated not the perceived
weakness of women, but their strength
and vital contribution to the war. But
then, women also replaced men in sports
leagues as well. For example, in 1943,
the All-American Girls Professional
Baseball League was formed, owing to
sports executives fears that Major
League Baseball would shut down entirely
during the war. Now, to be clear, women
have been organizing for baseball since
the 19th century, but this was the first
time all women professional leagues were
created. But here's where I tell you
that the league petered out once the war
was over since in the owner's minds,
women were only a temporary replacement
for men's leagues. But even so, this
created a strong foundation for the
expansion of professional women's sports
in the rest of the 20th century. And
then similar to what happened after
World War I, after this war, some women
would remain in the workforce and others
returned to their previous role. Okay.
The second group for whom mobilization
opened opportunities was black
Americans. So around 700,000 black
Americans joined the ranks of the US
military. Although combat units were, as
a rule, segregated by race. For example,
the Tuskegee Airmen was an all black air
combat unit that trained at the Tuskegee
Institute of Alabama. And despite their
segregated role, this unit fought with
distinction, destroying hundreds of
enemies both in the air and on the
ground. However, I probably don't need
to tell you that though they played a
vital role in the US military, the
presence of black soldiers raised
debates about racial segregation. For
example, black labor activist A. Philip
Randolph organized a 100,000 person
march on Washington DC to oppose
segregation in the military. But when
Roosevelt heard about it, he got real
annoyed because his whole message to the
public about the war was that we were
fighting for freedom and democracy. and
100,000 black people marching on
Washington saying they were not free and
their access to democracy was limited
would constitute no small amount of egg
on the presidential face. And so
Roosevelt issued Executive Order 8802
which did not desegregate the military
but did set up a regulatory board that
would investigate inequality in the
military. And after such a compromise,
Randolph canceled the march. However,
Randolph's march was merely a symbol of
a larger push for black civil rights,
namely the double V campaign, which
claimed that while America fought a
single front war against hostile powers
abroad, black Americans fought a
two-front war, both against foreign
enemies and domestic races. And these
campaigns, which worked to secure
democracy at home and abroad, laid the
groundwork for many of the successes
gained during the civil rights movement
in the next period. And then the third
group who benefited from mobilization
were Mexican immigrants. So agricultural
industries faced the exact same problem
industrial corporations and sports
leagues faced. Namely that all the male
workers were getting their he parts
shipped across the sea. And so the
government introduced the Brasero
program which invited Mexican laborers
to enter the country and work in needed
wartime industries, most notably
agriculture for a limited time. And this
is a stark reversal of depression era
policies that deported folks of Mexican
descent. And again, just like with women
and black Americans, despite the
economy's vital need for Mexican
workers, the sudden influx of so many of
them led to nivist resistance. And
probably the most notable example of
such resistance were the zoots suit
riots that occurred in California in
1943. So zoot suits have become
fashionable among Mexican-amean youth in
Los Angeles. And because the flowy suits
required more than a usual amount of
fabric to create American servicemen
stationed there accused them of being
unpatriotic in a time when cloth was
needed for the war effort. And so that
combined with a long-standing racial
bias against Mexican-Americans led white
servicemen to enter a neighborhood and
attack anyone they saw wearing a zoot
suit and many that were not. And soon
the Zoot suitors retaliated and thus
began four days of violence that was
part of a larger trend of race riots
that occurred in the summer of 1943. And
finally, the third big homeront effect
of mobilization was the repression of
American civil liberties. Now, to be
fair, government repression of civil
liberties during World War II was not as
widespread as it was during World War I.
However, some groups endured an outsized
attack on their civil liberties. And the
best example here is the wartime policy
of Japanese internment. So, for the most
part, Japanese Americans and immigrants
were clustered in communities on the
West Coast, and they were targeted for
internment for two reasons. First, they
were associated with the hated Japanese
enemy who had bombed Pearl Harbor and
killed 2400 American service people. And
this association was certainly not
helped by the rampant racism and wartime
propaganda which depicted Japanese
people and standard stereotypical tropes
meant to invoke fear in the American
public. And then second, while German
and Italian Americans were also
associated with America's wartime
enemies, they were more spread out
across the country by this point and
they were largely considered white. But
Japanese Americans unfortunately
satisfied neither of these categories.
And so because the government feared
that Japanese Americans might serve as
spies for the Japanese government,
Roosevelt signed Executive Order 90066.
It mandated that all Japanese people
must leave their homes and be relocated
to internment camps throughout the
Western States. And as a result,
something like 120,000 Japanese people
living in the United States, twothirds
of them US citizens, were forcibly
removed from their homes without cause
and then required to live in shoddy
camps erected to facilitate full-time
government surveillance. However, some
Japanese Americans challenged such
racist and unconstitutional behavior as
did Fred Cororamatsu. Like an absolute
boss, he decided to plant his hind parts
rioted home and refused to relocate to
the internment camps. And for such
intrigence, he was arrested and his plea
ultimately wound up before the Supreme
Court in a case called Koramatsu v. the
United States. Now, Cororamatsu's
lawyers argue that the government's
interament policy violated his fifth
amendment rights to due process before
the law and the right to a jury trial.
However, the Supreme Court upheld the
constitutionally of the interament of
American citizens as a wartime
necessity. However, I should also
mention that in 1988, the federal
government paid out $1.65 billion in
reparations to those citizens that had
interned. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other videos for unit 7 or you
can click here to grab my A pushheimler
review guide which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible. I'm
glad you came around and I'll catch you
on the flipflop.